Preliminary Guide to the Gelman Library Administration records, ca. 1825-2005 RG0119
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Gelman Library Administration records
circa 1825-2005
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
RG0119
297.5 Linear Feet
This collection contains the administrative records of Gelman Library. The materials include photographs, negatives, office records, building plans, posters, correspondence, and publications. They range in date from ca 1825-2005.
Restrictions on Access
Series 41 and 51 are closed to research for 25 years from date of record creation.. Series 53 and 54 are closed to research for 50 years from date of record creation.
Acquisition Information
Acquisition data is unknown.
Historical or Biographical Note
President Cloyd Heck Marvin, inaugurated in 1927, undertook a plan to bring the university curriculum and facilities up to 20th-century standards. A major part of the plan was the construction of a library building, the first in the University's history. In the fall semester of 1939, the Lisner Library, located on G Street between 20th and 21st streets, opened. The facility had a total of six floors and was entirely dedicated to library offices and stacks, which housed a collection of 119,000 volumes.
By 1954, the Library contained 270,000 volumes. One major increase came through the 1950 purchase of the library of the Carnegie Endowment for International Peace, adding more than 50,000 volumes to the stacks of both the Lisner Library and the Burns Library at the National Law Center.
In 1950, Matilda Wright donated to the Library her brother's collection of material on Washington, D.C., history. As the finest privately held collection of books, pamphlets, manuscripts, photographs, and artwork on the topic, these 1,500 items formed the core around which the Special Collections Department was built.
Despite this progress, the University Library compared unfavorably to other universities in terms of funding, staff, and collections. This was due to the faulty belief that the rich library resources of Washington were accessible to GW students and faculty as a substitute for onsite collections.
It was not until the beginning of Lloyd H. Elliott's presidency, in 1965, however, that significant improvement began to be made. Elliott declared that the development of a true research library for the University was his first priority. In 1966, he implemented a plan to increase the book budget. He also set up a building committee to develop a new research library building that could hold 1,000,000 volumes and seat 2,500 readers. The new Gelman Library opened in the fall of 1973 with a collection of 429,778 volumes. The following year, the collection passed the 500,000 volume mark. Mrs. Estelle Gelman, endowed the Library with $1,500,000 for unrestricted library development in 1980. The Library recognized the importance of her contribution by naming the University Library in honor of her late husband, Melvin Gelman. In 1984, Gelman Library marked the addition of its one-millionth volume to the collection and the library has been expanding rapidly ever since. A major acquisition was a gift from Ari and Phyllis Kiev of the I. Edward Kiev Collection on Judaica, which contains more than 20,000 volumes on religion, philosophy, classics and art.
In 2001, the Gelman Library raised funds for the two-millionth volume, An Illustrated Atlas; Geographical Statistical and Historical, of the Unites States, and the Adjacent Countries by T. G. Bradford; Boston, Weeks, Jordan [1838], and the two-million-and-first volume, Web of Science. The official Two-millionth Volume of The Gelman Library System is a rare book acquired through a gift from James Cecil King, a grateful alumnus, professor emeritus, bibliophile, writer and an ardent patron of The Melvin Gelman Library.
Collection Scope and Content
This collection contains the administrative records of Gelman Library. The materials include photographs, negatives, office records, building plans, posters, correspondence, and publications. They range in date from ca 1825-2005.
Collection Organization
This collection is organized into 56 series (there is no series 2). They include eighteen series of office records, eleven series with photographs, three series with negatives, two series with correspondence, two series of newsletters, and two series of posters. Single series include manuals; construction specifications; grant files; remodeling documents; by-laws; systems project; event materials; proposals; building plans; publication layouts; records and memos; blueprints; videotape; accession logs; t-shirts; and Andrea Stewart records
Melvin Gelman Library; Lisner Library; Photographs; Foggy Bottom (Washington, D.C.); Washington (D.C.); Gelman Library; George Washington University. Library; George Washington University
- Office files, circa 1825-2004; RG0119 Series 1; 5 Linear feet (Box 5, Box 1, Box 2, Box 3, Box 4)
  Scope and Contents note
  This series contains annual reports, correspondence, budgets, agendas, reports, guidelines, forms, committee reports, plans, surveys, registration card, brochures, mission statement, strategic plans, bookmarks, newsletters, bookplates, statistics, list library staff, organization charts, strategic planning, instructions, comment cards, buttons, studies, memorandums, procedures, conference proceedings, handbooks, programs, news articles, press releases, stickers, guides, proposals, and floor plans. They range in date from circa 1825 to 2004. The items concern the Administrative Council, work schedules, Gelman Library, library policies, job performance, job descriptions, Anglo-American Cataloging Rues 2 (AACR2), OCLC, RLG, RLIN, automation systems, incident reports, Jacob Burns Law Library annual reports, Himmelfarb Health Sciences Library (Medical Library) annual reports, Hospital Library annual reports, Acquisitions, serials, Circulation Department, reserve desk, International Relations collection, Catalog Department, donors, Reference Department, the institute for Sino-Soviet Studies Library, exhibits, library partnerships, cataloging, Study of bar code and light pen circulation systems, continuing eductions, preservation, conservation, audiovisual materials, Council of the Librarians, librarian ethics, disaster recovery plan, library exhibits, faculty orientation, Linser Library, inventories, the Library Council, Columbian College, Media Resources Department, the move to H Street, staff party events, one millionth book, two millionth book, Gelman Library's tenth anniversary, library staff, system operations, telecommunications, Television News Study Center, and University Librarians.
  Formerly vertical files
  - Library, University, 09/06/1966-04/23/2004 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Library, University--Administrative Council, 1979-1980, 10/11/1979-12/04/1980 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Library, University--Administrative Council, 1981, 01/08/1981-12/10/1981 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Library, University--Administrative Council, 1982, 01/07/1982-11/11/1982 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Library, University--Administrative Council, 1983, 01/05/1983-12/15/1983 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Library, University--Administrative Council, 1984, 01/19/1984-09/06/1984 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Library, University - Africana Research Center, 09/2001-03/31/2003 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Library, University--Annual Report, 1907, 05/08/1907-06/01/1907 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Library, University--Annual Report, 1908, 06/01/1907-05/28/1908 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Library, University--Annual Report, 1909, 02/06/1909-10/09/1909 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Library, University--Annual Report, 1910, 01/08/1910-05/10/1910 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Library, University--Annual Report, 1914, 11/11/1913-10/12/1914 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Library, University--Annual Report, 1916, 10/15/1915-01/14/1916 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Library, University--Annual Report, 1917, 12/05/1917 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Library, University--Annual Report, 1928, 06/30/1928 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Library, University--Annual Report, 1929, 06/29/1929 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Library, University--Annual Report, 1930, 06/30/1930 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Library, University--Annual Report, 1931, 10/18/1929-06/30/1931 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Library, University--Annual Report, 1932, 1931-06/30/1932 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Library, University--Annual Report, 1933, 09/16/1932-11/1933 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Library, University--Annual Report, 1934, 07/03/1933-06/30/1934 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Library, University--Annual Report, 1935, 1923-06/30/1935 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Library, University--Annual Report, 1936, 01/18/1935-06/30/1936 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Library, University--Annual Report, 1937, 1936-1937 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Library, University--Annual Report, 1938, 11/11/1937-06/30/1938 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Library, University--Annual Report, 1939, 1938-1939 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Library, University--Annual Report, 1940, 1939-1940 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Library, University--Annual Report, 1941, 04/08/1940-06/30/1941 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Library, University--Annual Report, 1942, 11/26/1940-08/01/1942 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Library, University--Annual Report, 1943, 1941-07/15/1943 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Library, University--Annual Report, 1944, 08/02/1943-07/15/1944 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Library, University--Annual Report, 1945, 07/18/1944-07/15/1945 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Library, University--Annual Report, 1946, 1939-07/15/1946 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Library, University--Annual Report, 1947, 06/06/1946-09/01/1947 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Library, University--Annual Report, 1948, 06/23/1947-08/15/1948 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Library, University--Annual Report, 1949, 1943-08/01/1949 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Library, University--Annual Report, 1950, 1948-09/22/1950 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Library, University--Annual Report, 1951, 07/10/1950-10/15/1951 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Library, University--Annual Report, 1952, 01/18/1951-07/31/1952 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Library, University--Annual Report, 1953, 01/21/1952-07/31/1953 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Library, University--Annual Report, 1954, 1953-10/14/1954 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Library, University--Annual Report, 1955, 1953-05/31/1955 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Library, University--Annual Report, 1956, 1954-09/12/1956 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Library, University--Annual Report, 1957, 01/10/1956-05/31/1957 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Library, University--Annual Report, 1958, 05/01/1957-06/01/1958 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Library, University--Annual Report, 1959, 01/05/1958-09/18/1959 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Library, University--Annual Report, 1960, 01/20/1959-06/24/1960 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Library, University--Annual Report, 1961, 12/15/1959-03/16/1962 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Library, University--Annual Report, 1962, 01/05/1961-07/18/1962 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Library, University--Annual Report, 1963, 1954-07/08/1963 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Library, University--Annual Report, 1964, 09/27/1961-05/31/1964 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Library, University--Annual Report, 1965, 04/15/1964-09/13/1965 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Library, University--Annual Reports, 1966, 12/17/1964-02/14/1967 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Library, University--Annual Report, 1967, 12/21/1965-08/10/1967 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Library, University--Annual Report, 1968-1972, 1967-01/1973 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Library, University--Annual Report, 1973-1976, 1972-1976 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Library, University--Annual Report, 1977, 1976-1977 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Library, University--Annual Report, 1978, 1977 1978 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Library, University--Annual Report, 1979, 1978-1980 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Library, University--Annual Report, 1981, 1980-1981 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Library, University--Annual Report, 1990, 06/03/1990 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Library, University--Annual Report, 1993, 07/30/1993 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Library, University--Annual Report, 1994, 07/08/1994 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Library, University--Annual Report, 1995, 07/10/1995 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Library, University--Annual Report, 1996, 07/26/1996 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Library, University--Annual Report, 1997, 06/24/1997 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Library, University--Annual Report, 1998, 06/23/1998 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Library, University--Annual Report, 2000, 06/21/2000 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Library, University--Annual Report, 2001, 06/18/2001 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Library, University--Annual Report, 2002, 06/17/2002 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Library, University--Annual Report, 2003, 07/16/2003 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Library, University--Annual Report, 2004, 06/14/2004 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Library, University--Budget, 1905-1921, 11/25/1905-1921 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Library, University--Cataloging, 08/20/1974-02/17/1989 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Library, University--Circulation Dept., 05/11/1970-07/1976 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Library, University--Committees, 08/07/1974-02/1987 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Library, University--Committees--Exhibits, 01/25/1974-04/11/1978 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Library, University--Committees--Social, 05/06/1977-02/28/1978 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Library, University--Conferences, 05/12/1988 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Library, University--Continuing education, 07/05/1974-1979 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Library, University--Conservation program, Gelman Library, 1980-03/01/1983 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Library, University - Consortium of Universities of Washington, DC - Interuniversity Library Council Minutes, 1964-1968, 02/04/1964-12/12/1968 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Library, University - Consortium of Universities of Washington, DC - Library Council Minutes, 1969-1975, 02/06/1969-04/01/1977 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Library, University - Consortium of Universities of Washington Metropolitan area, 07/06/1970-10/01/1987 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Library, University - Consortium of Universities of Washington Metropolitan area - Guide to Library Resources, 09/1972-1989 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Library, University - Consortium of Universities of Washington Metropolitan area - Newsletters, 07/1983-04/1984 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Library, University - Council of Librarians, 1975-09/17/1994 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Library, University - Departmental monthly reports, 1975-March 1978, 12/1975-03/1978 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Library, University - Departmental monthly reports, 1978 [September-December], 09/1978-12/1978 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Library, University - Departmental monthly reports, 1979 [January-March], 01/1979-03/1979 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Library, University - Departmental monthly reports, 1979 [April-June], 04/1979-06/1979 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Library, University - Disaster plan, 1994-10/17/1995 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Library, University - Exhibitions in the George Washington University Library, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Library, University - Exhibits, 1944-68, 05/13/1944-01/05/1968 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Library, University - Exhibits, 1973-91, 09/12/1973-06/17/1991 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Library, University - Faculty relations, 09/12/1973-08/25/1984 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Library, University - Gifts, 1936-11/24/1995 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Library, University - History, 10/25/1823-2002 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Library, University - Inventories, 01/18/1974-05/16/1982 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Library, University - Library Council - Meeting minutes [1967-1975], 01/31/1967-01/22/1976 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Library, University - Library Council - Meeting minutes [1976-1979], 01/29/1976-08/16/1979 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Library, University - Library guides, 07/1973-08/04/2003 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Library, University - Library guide - Faculty guide to the library, 09/1979-2003 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Library, University - Library guide - Student guide to the library, 1987-1998 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Library, University - List of books of the original Columbian College, 1825 ca.-1988 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Library, University - Move to 2130 H St., 12/01/1971-10/08/1973 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Library, University - Naming of the Melvin Gelman Library, May 14, 1980, 05/14/1980-09/1980 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Library, University - New Library - Program Statement for a proposed general library building for GW, 1967 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Library, University - Organization charts, 03/1972-12/08/1982 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Library, University - Policies and procedures manual, 01/10/1977-01/1983 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Library, University - Reference department, 1973-1982 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Library, University - Reference department - Bibliographies, 01/1988-03/07/1995 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Library, University - Regulations and policies, 1967-1992 --ca. (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Library, University - Renovations, 1987-1988 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Library, University - Safety & security, 09/09/1975-10/06/1978 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Library, University - Schedules, 08/14/1973-05/16/2004 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Library, University - Special events, 12/20/1946-11/25/2003 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Library, University - Special events - Millionth and two millionth volumes, 03/28/1984-10/19/2001 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Library, University - Special events - Tenth anniversary, 01/30/1984-03/30/1984 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Library, University - Strategic plans [1974-1975], 01/21/1974-05/27/1975 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Library, University - Strategic plans [1989-2000], 08/23/1989-09/2000 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Library, University - Staff, 11/1969-01/21/1983 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Library, university - subject specialists, 07/1985-12/1989 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Library, university - survey of the external environment of Gelman Library, 1986, 02/1986 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Library, university - Systems Operations Group (SOG), 05/12/1985-11/12/1987 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Library, university - Telecommunications Information Center, 05/07/1982-05/1983 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Library, university - University librarian - Alslip, James (1979-1983), 07/16/1979-08/09/1983 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Library, university - University librarian - Freeby, Harriet (1905/06 - 1906/07) - first librarian (GWU), 06/01/1949 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Library, university - University librarian - Mason, John Russell (1933-1966), 03/09/1974-10/1981 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Library, university - University librarian - Schmidt, Alfred F.W. (1906-1933), 02/23/1907-12/1973 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Library, university - University librarian - Woodward, Rupert C. (1967-1979), 01/1968-03/1981 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Library, university - University librarian - Woodward, Rupert C. - university library memoranda, 1967-1973, 03/01/1967-12/20/1973 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Library, university - University librarian - Woodward, Rupert C. - university library memoranda, 1974-1977, 01/10/1974-12/21/1977 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Library, university - User surveys, 04/08/1987-05/14/1991 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Library, university - Washington Research Library Consortium (WRLC), 10/12/1987-02/29/1996 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Library, university - Washington Research Library Consortium (WRLC) - Guide to WRLC Libraries, 1990-2001 (Box 5, Folder 14)
- Manuals, 1979-1985; RG0119 Series 3; 4.5 Linear feet
  This series includes binders of computer systems manuals, proposals, including CL systems/libs 100, GEAC computers library information systems, wang/vs100, NSC computer systems, and Notis. They range in date 1979-1985.
  Formerly ACC#154
  This series has a container list in electronic form, please ask staff for assistance.
- Office records, 1966-1988; RG0119 Series 4; 1.5 Linear feet
  This series consists of office files and includes information concerning the council of deans and librarians, committees, dedications of Alfred Schmidt and John Russell Mason rooms, and Institute for Sino-Soviet studies. They range in date from 1966-1988.
  Formerly ACC#200
  - Charles E. Smith donation to the Judaic Studies book fund, 1976-1977 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Council of Deans, 1984-1988 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Council of Librarians, 1975-1979 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Dedication of the Alfred F.W. Schmidt Memorial Room, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Dedication of the John Russell Mason room, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    General note
    Photos and articles
  - Executive Commitee, 1976-1982 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Foreign Service History Center, 1987-1988 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Foreign Service History Center, 1984-1986 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Goals for the University Library, 1968-1970 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Graduate Fellowship Information Center, 1983-1984 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Graduate Fellowship Information Center, 1980-1983 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Institute for Sino-Soviet Studies, 1966-1983 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Inventory of non-book materials in Special Collections, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Library Council, 1975-1979 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Luther Rice Bicentennial Planning Committee, 1982-1983 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Media Resources and Television News Study Center, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Serials Department, 1979-1985 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Social Committee, 1981-1982 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Subject Specialists, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Television News Study Center, 1980-1982 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Administration office files, undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Washington Star Library, 1981-1982 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Photographs, 1970-1979; RG0119 Series 5; 1.5 Linear feet (Box 1)
  This series includes photographs of the library and receptions (Blackwell, Crain, Small). They range in date from the 1970's.
  Formerly ACC#230
  This series has a paper container list in the reading room, please ask staff for assistance.
- Construction specifications, 1971-1978; RG0119 Series 6; 1.75 Linear feet (Box 2, Box 1)
  This series includes construction specifications for Gelman Library in 1971. It also includes specifications for library audio-video expansion (with blueprints) from 1978.
  Formerly ACC#273
  - Construction specifications for Gelman Library, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Specifications for library audio-video division expansion, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Specifications for library audio-video division expansion, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Blueprints
- Office records, 1986-1992; RG0119 Series 7; 4.5 Linear feet
  This series includes a gift log, library update, user surveys, planning documents, Connect newsletter, department monthly reports, and student donations. They range in date from 1986-1992.
  Formerly ACC#319
- Office records, 1987-1992; RG0119 Series 8; 1.5 Linear feet
  This series includes strategic planning for Gelman Library (including mission statements of various departments, undergraduate and graduate studies, user surveys, services provided, policies and procedures, environmental scans of outside forces impacting the library). They range in date from 1987-1992.
  Formerly ACC#331
  This series is unprocessed, please ask staff for assistance.
- Grant files, 1980-1992; RG0119 Series 9; 3 Linear feet
  This series includes grant files and applications (Carnegie pamphlet collection, collections dc database, archives records management program, etc.). They range in date from 1980-1992.
  Formerly ACC#332
- Remodeling documents, 1985-1986; RG0119 Series 10; 1.5 Linear feet (Box 1)
  This series includes Gelman Library remodeling documents. They range in date from 1985-1986.
  Formerly ACC#343
- Posters, 1993; RG0119 Series 11; .25 Linear feet (Box 1)
  This series includes information on "Celebrating Twenty Years" - Gelman Library anniversary posters from 1993.
  Formerly ACC#345
  - "Celebrating Twenty Years", 1993 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    10 copies
- By-laws, 1995; RG0119 Series 12; 1.5 Linear feet (Box 1)
  This series includes code and by-laws committee materials from 1995.
  Formerly ACC#349
  - Code and by-laws committee materials, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 1)